Weekend.
Okay.
So
one second.
I'm gonna go to the calendar.
>> I heard Scott.
Alright. So we're gonna get started with the Board of Selectmen
Special Budget Workshop meeting
on Monday,
February
27.
We're gonna get started at
07:13.
We had a little bit of technical difficulty.
We're gonna start with
the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of The United States Of America and to the republic for which it stands,
nation under God, indivisible with liberty and justice for all.
Thank you very much. And now we're going to move to item two public speak, Elaine Bucart.
>> Hi, I just wanted to listen to see where you're at in the budget process at this point. And of course,
you know,
we're pushing for a part time planning economic development consultant
or part time employee.
So,
that's what I'm listening for. Thanks. You got it. Joanne Ebert.
I'm all set. Thank you.
Just listening.
>> Alright.
Eric,
after our last meeting,
we had asked for certain
guidance from you. So if do you wanna sit there and take control of the meeting and put up the data that you wanna put up for us?
Sure.
What do you want to start with?
>> Well,
are we gonna push all of the public works, roadwork off till
>> Jay can be on? Yeah. We're gonna have to. I mean, we just haven't had time to that's gonna that's gonna be an expense extensive,
you know, to put a full blown plan back together for you guys. That's gonna take us a bit of time.
>> Okay.
I
cannot move that.
Do
you have your can you put up on your screen your, budget spreadsheet?
Certainly.
Okay. That should be the budget spreadsheet.
Okay.
>> So what would you like to look at? You wanna just go down through it line by line, or what do you want? Let's go through it section by section if we can.
Okay. We'll start at the top.
Let me just
okay. So
>> first up We talked about your budget is budget revenue
shortfalls. We did talk about that. Right.
>> You know, unfortunately,
a lot of this, we just don't know yet.
I mean, because we're still at a preliminary,
the state budget hasn't come out yet. So we're just making
guesses
on a bunch of this stuff.
So,
the bottom line is if this is,
you know, accurate, we're looking at somewhere around 2,400,000,
2,420,000
in
revenues from things other than taxation.
When we get to expenses,
as we all know, the two biggest single line items
are education
at the RAM Board of Ed,
and then education
at the Andover Elementary School.
I did notice that
the elementary
school board of ED did publish a
draft
budget.
That
was 4,234,000
so it was just basically just about $1,000
less than the initial estimate
that I had.
So I put that in
the the exact number from them.
Okay. There is still a
Ram hasn't come out with any kind of finalized budget yet,
but my casual
conversation
with
Colm, the superintendent,
indicates that
we can expect it to drop at least a percent, maybe a percent and a half
from what's listed
there.
You know, but there's nothing final because they haven't made any kind of final decision yet
at this point.
Administrators
contract.
My contract is signed,
that's just what the number
is.
My admin assistant,
you know you we still haven't as a town
or as a board set the
pay raises
for the non union non contract employees,
So I used 3%
as an estimate for all of that, but obviously that depends on what the board wants to do, whether you wanna go lower or higher.
>> So let's
put off until we can sit there and have everybody
having a conversation about
non union employee
pay rates. So, you know, send us what I would ask you to do is send us all an email on the individuals that qualify for that. So I'm assuming we have Jay, we have the administrative assistant. I don't think we have very many others, do we?
We actually do because you gotta sit there and go. There are some other people that are non union that what is the what is the increase we plan on giving? So we have to come up with a number related to that.
>> Right. Are we we look are we looking for one number? Are we adjusting based on, you know, time on job and such and such as well?
>> We can do it any way we choose to do. I mean,
you know, it's a question of what your percentage is going to be, Adrian. So or we give each individual an evaluation or we ask Eric to give us what those numbers are, and then we decide whether we go with Eric's numbers or not.
>> And so you had two spreadsheets
that were given to you when the original budget was drafted.
The first was called town personnel costs, healthcare and benefits before.
And
the
second was
town
personnel costs,
how did I word that something wacky.
Healthcare
and no.
Again.
Non contracted personnel raises.
That is the one that shows
the various
scenarios
for employees and what it looks like.
I could share that screen now if you wanted to look at that, or we can review that at some other time.
>> I would personally like to sit there and work on that at a different meeting.
Okay.
I mean, if you could go through the
non employee cost
items and sit there and tell us if you have any significant increases or decreases in any of the line items, then that would be things that we
should talk about and we should get to. I mean, it doesn't look to be very many
changes that you're making that are
of substance. Then what we have to do is get back everybody and decide,
do we have any areas where anybody has any
desire to make changes? Like,
you know, what are our priorities? Are there priorities that individual members of the board have? And do we wanna sit there and act upon them?
>> So if
we start talking about that and we scroll right down under the tax collectors line item,
we are assuming that the tax collector is retiring at some point in the fall.
So we are going to put in extra money in the conference seminar line item, because I know my admin assistant is interested in
possibly becoming the tax collector.
And that might be something that works for the town that
no decision certainly has been made on that yet,
but that would.
You know, cover the first of
the.
The course series
that you have to get to be certified as a tax collector
now you don't have to be certified day you start the job, but you do have to obtain certification
in a reasonable time so that allows that that's the line item, you see up there under
conference slash seminars.
You know that's the only big real increase
under the tax collector
budget.
In the assessors line item, there's a bump up for training.
There's also a couple thousand dollars in contract software maintenance.
Those are the
contracts that we have for both QDS and Vision.
And they gave us finally numbers for that.
So those are based on the contracts,
what those companies would charge us in the next year.
The other one that went up a lot was the subscription
to the
NADA
books,
which we are required
to have and maintain.
You know the company got bought out and
they jacked up the
the rates.
>> Isn't there going to be a change to how
the state is dealing
with automotive
assessments?
Isn't that something? Maybe.
>> Maybe.
Yes.
There is one thing that might come into effect this year.
Although,
as I understand it they're talking about a legislative change not have it come into this year,
because the.
Companies
that do
tax software
aren't ready for it yet.
And so they're arguing they can't actually deal with it yet.
Which,
I don't want to argue one way or the other. I don't know where that's going. So
that's out there.
Maybe we don't need it.
If
the change really does go into effect next year,
we're not going to need to buy the books. But if we do have to buy the books, they're a lot more expensive going forward. That's fine. 300. The
registrar's
office and elections
are both
kind of sketchy to estimate right now.
Register less so than the elections,
because
we still don't have any idea what's going to pass
in terms of early election.
Results.
There's a bunch of different bills. I've read through them all. The
worst one for us would require us to staff the polling place for two weeks straight prior to the election.
That would be a very expensive thing if the town has to do it.
The least costly one to us would just do it all via
mail in ballot. That would be essentially cost neutral for doing. So
we put in
some increases
for both registrar
and elections,
but without actually really knowing what that's going to be, that number is really variable right now.
But this represents a
slight increase,
but something that doesn't radically change the way we have to hold elections.
So,
that's, you know, the elections category.
In the building department,
that the
shared service
for the building official
assumes a 3% increase and an increase for one additional hour.
That was a request from Bolton.
Depending on what you want to do, we could push back on that.
It just depends where you want to go with that.
I don't know whether they would,
you know, I know they're desperately trying to hire another
building
official
right now. And the reason is Jim Ruper,
who was their essentially chief building official,
took over as the town administrator.
So now they just have Randy and they have a couple part time people helping cover right now.
So they're
looking to hire another full time employee for that.
That's that. I
>> don't see why we'd push back. I think we're getting a pretty good deal out of them right now. So, you know, I'm happy they're working with us.
>> I agree. And I actually think what they're giving us is really good service.
You know, and I think it's worth it, but you know, but it is a significant increase,
you know, not
trying to say it's not.
The admin
assistant,
we actually had.
More money.
You know.
It's a union position.
We don't have it fully. We don't know what's going to come out of the union, but that's a that's if nothing else changes that would cover
what
you know what we're proposing with the Union goes
that will cover it. And
that's pretty much it for the building department, other than you see I did put the town planner
line item there.
We
did elect to put the wages for both the zoning agent
in the Inland Wetlands And Watercourse Agent in
that
under the building department.
Because a while back, you would ask me what our costs were for the building department as a whole.
You know, so I thought it would be
be smart to include the majority of the costs within the building department and put it all in that one department. As opposed to the way it's been in the past was
the zoning agent
was under the planning and zoning commission,
but he's not really a part of the Commission he's an employee of the town that works
essentially in the building and land use office so that's how I did it conceptually.
If you guys are unhappy with that we can certainly change that back.
>> No, I like it there.
I mean, at least my opinion is that's
appropriate spot for it. I mean, because I would ask you what is the
is the revenue generated by the building department? Does it cover that 135 right now? Let's sit there and take out 30,000. Does it cover a $100,000?
>> No.
Definitely not right now, but part of that is building is off now.
But,
yeah, we can,
you know, we can certainly going forward revisit
themes.
You know, it's definitely harder to cover
the costs of the zoning agent
and
the wetlands agent than it is to cover the costs of the building department.
But,
you know, of the building official, I should say, and the admin system.
>> Yeah. We we probably we've we probably should be reviewing fees again. I mean, it's something we should kinda so,
I'll be happy to work on that with you again, Eric, if you wanna do that again.
>> Yep
not.
Not
a problem.
Library payroll
I've got to review that that doesn't seem quite right,
we do,
because most of the library employees.
Are
making less than what will be the current what will be the $15 an hour minimum wage
on July 1,
a lot of those employees are brought up to the $15 an hour to comply with state law.
I
asked the library
for a list of the number of hours
approximately by each of their employees. And
when I multiplied it through by their costs, that's what I get, 79.4.
So that's what I budgeted.
>> They didn't submit, but they
I thought the library normally submits a budget now.
>> They submit an operations
budget,
but because their employees get paid directly by the town.
They just
in in because they do not set their own salaries,
you as a board set all their salaries.
There's no real way for them to submit a payroll budget.
So what I ask them to do is basically,
by employee,
how many hours do they anticipate working in a year? And then I do the math. Okay.
>> That was the question. So they're telling you how many hours they need or whatever, and you're doing Correct. The But you have to get them up to the minimum wage.
Yes.
Correct.
>> So get them up to the minimum wage and then give us the number.
>> Yes.
That should be the number.
So
if you
looked at
>> can you see that screen, or are you still on the other screen? Still on the other screen.
Okay. So anyway, if
if that is the number with their their wages at minimum wage, then that's
the baseline.
>> That is correct.
Yes,
that's what it calculates out at based on the number of hours per week that they've given me per employee.
And I can show you that screen if you wanna see that screen instead.
>> No. We don't wanna I don't wanna put that up individual information.
K. I just wanna know that if you're calculating that out and that
I mean, I don't know how the library
I don't know why the library wouldn't do a full blown,
mean, they should at least sit there and say this is what we'd like to get our employees to be paid.
And then here are the hours, the estimated hours
anticipate them working and give us a budget that we can go through. I mean,
because I guess I would ask you, Eric, go back to the library board and say, this the number that works for wages?
Anyway, okay, let's go through that. Let's get through that one. The next one you're in control of.
>> Civil preparedness,
that's not changing very much. I think that's a 3% increase in salary.
Everything else basically stays the same.
It's
not a particularly big budget.
So town office building,
we're pretty well
flat line.
Are a bunch of things that I don't have hard numbers yet for that I asked for.
Like I asked for what
their expectations
are for the computer tech support, again, assuming the same rough numbers that we have right now.
You know I don't have
the numbers yet for the payroll service,
so a lot of this stuff.
You know I don't
know
specifically
I mean some of the bigger ones like
talent dispatch I know that number now.
You know a lot of the others are you know we're just based
in we know.
As far as electricity
our guests should be fairly good.
The one of the unknowns is the fuel oil because we are still forecasting
a changeover to a ductless split.
And that will knock the fuel oil down pretty considerably.
I kind of split the difference between what we had and what were
proposed,
assuming that we can, you know, we don't end up changing out the boiler,
but we end up putting in the ductless splits
and,
you know, we generate a significant fraction of our heating load with the ductless splits.
>> Did you make an adjustment to the electric bill accordingly?
>> Yes,
so we guessed really high
for the electric bill for last year.
So I did bump that up somewhat.
You know and I'm also assuming that when we get past the six month on our
cost
per kilowatt is going to drop back down considerably
because.
You
know I just I don't see that rate being staying really high.
You know we're not as affected anyway, because we're locked in with constellation
Constellation
has What are we little bit, but it looks like it's gonna come back down again also.
What are we locked in at?
>> You had to ask.
I don't know off the top of my head what we're paying for,
you know, our supply.
>> I was gonna say, like, I I just locked in at 13,
you know, I mean, so if we if we're not stuck in a contract, we should be looking a little bit, you know?
>> Yeah. No. The way it works is we
pay
I think we
do it through CCM.
We pay CCM,
who has a contract
goes out to contract every two years
with a company
that
essentially looks at all the electric
suppliers
in New England
and negotiates
for all of the
CCM
member towns that want to participate.
We've had that arrangement with Constellation for a bunch of years.
And it is a pretty good rate.
I don't know exactly what it is today,
but it's
certainly
a lot less hassle
and you have somebody that's paid to monitor that
and put the RFPs out to keep your costs as low as possible.
Okay.
You know, computer replacement services,
we've kept most of that the same.
We did bump up janitorial supplies because just looking at the bills that Willie's submitting,
I think we're 1,600
was a little low for the maintenance for this building.
Computer repair service, we've been doing fairly well because
at this point, we've done a pretty good job of updating all the PCs
here.
So this is just what it takes for us to maintain,
which nets us essentially three computers per year
across the departments.
And that does not include the town clerk's office because
they don't play well
with us.
Legal advertising,
no change. Insurance.
So
I
>> we
must have overestimated
it a little bit last year, because when I do the math this year, I keep coming out with, I don't have a set of bills yet for Kerma.
We're not going to get them for a couple of
months still.
But with Kerma,
we have a cost cap for
both the liability
and automobile policy and the workers' comp policy.
So even if we assume the max increase
they could possibly give us this year
and assume a 5% increase for ESIP,
it only comes out to about $113,000
So
don't know where we got last year's figure, to be perfectly honest.
I've
put a note to myself that I wanna revisit that to make sure that there's nothing that I'm missing,
but that covers our major insurance costs.
Employee benefits,
looks like as far as the health and dental,
we're looking overall at about a 3%
increase
this year in total healthcare costs.
If you remember last year,
it was basically zero.
So
that means, you know, over the last two years, it's been either, you know, 3% or zero.
Overall, I think they're doing fairly well
with the
healthcare costs.
I know we had looked and some people
had thought we should consider getting out of the consortium and going to the state program that's run for the municipalities,
but that program the last year or so has had some
really bad claims history.
So I think that's probably not a great idea because that looks like the costs for that program are going up this year fairly considerably.
>> Have we received any kind of refund
related to the consortium?
What do you mean refund?
>> Well, you're basically in a self insurance pool. Has there been any savings that they've
contributed back to the participating
groups?
>> Not to the groups, but they've used that to fund
essentially
the pool.
And they just essentially what they do is they adjust the following year's rates
based on what they need to do to keep the pool at a certain amount.
So we haven't gotten any rebates per se.
>> How
long have we been participating in this now? Is this year four?
Year five?
Somewhere in there, yeah.
>> I mean, because they said when they started this that after year three, would be rebates back to the participants.
Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. But then people got sick. So
>> Yeah. But Yeah.
Know, depends upon
how sick Adrian. Right? And and did we get lucky or did we not? I mean, that that's
so,
anyway,
it's a it's a question that should be asked. Like, are there are there any plans for
rebates?
Because it's self insurance.
>> Okay.
Right.
Okay.
Old town hall, not a real lot of difference other than they zeroed out the fuel oil bill completely because they never seem to operate it or run the damn thing in the winter and there's a full tank now. So I don't see any reason why we have to account for fuel for that for next year.
Town garage,
increase the conference and seminars.
I think there's a lot of training through the T2 Center at UConn that I would like to start cycling their employees through.
You know, it's just a question of time.
And do you want to carve it out? Not a huge expense, but it's something I think we should,
you know, should consider.
Yeah, nothing real earth shaking in that budget.
There is an increase in fuel,
but we did that based on actual usage.
So even though our cost
per gallon of fuel has increased about a buck,
You know, based on the last couple of years, three years of data,
you know, we think 7,500
should cover it.
So that's that
old firehouse.
The only thing I'm really doing is I'm keeping electricity
on until such point as we demolished the building.
Because I think all
the asbestos abatement contractors
basically said, if there's no building power
source provided,
and there's no water provided, your costs
to demo are considerably higher.
So hopefully within the next year, we get that building torn down. We essentially zero that out
completely for the old firehouse.
Eric, has that been winterized?
Yes.
>> Okay. Just wanna make sure everything's been drained down for next week.
>> Yep. Power's off.
So that's been drained down for a couple of years. Okay. I just wanna make sure. Yep.
I think I don't have any numbers yet on the auditor.
I'm assuming we can get away without really spending much more on your audit,
because I think we're going to be giving it to him in a condition
that is going to make their lives enough happier that they're not going to charge us more money than they're charging now.
That's my goal anyway.
So as far as the town's attorney budget, I think the legal retainer,
you know, still works
for the town's attorney,
you know, and providing some legal advice
from other venues, the other venue being the town's personnel
attorney.
You know, as you know,
there's a separate legal budget for the assessor's office,
and
I propose keeping that at 2,000
I don't know of anything right now that's going to require us to expend
money out of that, but,
you know,
so
that hasn't really changed.
Town engineering fees,
I'm keeping it the same.
Up to this point, we haven't been expending money out of the budget.
But I think now that we're using the town engineer a lot more,
that's going to become questionable.
But I also think that a lot of things we're going to chart are going to be charged to the appropriate category,
like all the work he's doing for the culverts that gets charged against the culvert account,
not against just the town engineer.
So this covers, like, general fees for the town engineer.
So I kept that the same.
Crog CCM cost.
I have the thing for cost already.
I don't have it for CCM
or Crog.
Those budget meetings have not occurred yet,
so I don't know what the final,
you know, but those have been holding pretty similar
the past few years,
So
I'm assuming they're gonna stay roughly the same as what they are now.
When you get down to
public works,
salary
line item,
you can see the assumptions there,
which is that we end up around 3% or 2.9%
of the union contracts,
and '23
and
twenty three-twenty four,
and a 5%
increase
for
Jay Tuttle.
As far as the temp salary goes,
Jay put this in there because he
had a conversation
with Scott Prashant.
And Scott Persson was trying to figure out whether we could get somebody in there specifically
to cover
the field maintenance
portion
and bring on a temp
person for the summer to deal with.
You know, dealing with the irrigation system
in there
I'm not sure that's appropriate,
I mean we need to keep about $2,500
in that that budget
to deal with when we
hire outside people for traffic control.
But to me, I would I would keep it at that.
>> I mean, is is that an is that an appropriate place to put it? Shouldn't that be under rec or something like that?
>> Well,
I don't know where to put that.
You know, I'm not sure I would put it in there, period.
But I understand that Scott's
frustrated
with the amount of work he's ended up doing
dealing with the field.
You know, and that that's perfectly valid. Just don't know exactly how to address that concern.
I don't think necessarily hiring temp employee to do that
is the way to go,
I don't know.
You know, I was hoping he was on the call to
be part of that discussion. I think that you should kind of punt until you can get Scott to tell He's you what he's on the call. Got Okay.
I guess I don't see you on there.
Am I missing it?
>> Oh, yeah. He's there. I don't know if he's muted or not.
Scott, can you chime in?
>> I mean, I sit there with Scott, and I go, why wouldn't we want public works or some version of public works, whether it's a temp individual or someone from,
you know, you're gonna sit there, everybody's gonna sit there and go, we need them to do the work that's important, which is the roads and the culverts and the drainage and but
that work down there should be done by
someone supervised by Jay Tuttle.
But what work exactly?
>> Any work
related to that irrigation system
should be if if needed That's not that's
that's not public works, though. Why not? I
>> mean, we don't have a we don't have a
parks and rec department, so why wouldn't
>> Way over their pay grade.
No. Or should I say under their pay or under their pay grade, I should say. I apologize.
>> Well
so then the only one who's an employee in the town that would be under their pay grade to manage that would be Eric. So it's either Eric or Jay. We don't have a lot of options.
>> Or you hire it out.
What I mean, we need an idea of exactly what we're supposed to be doing down there that we're not doing. Making that list, then let's let's put that off the contract.
You know?
>> Okay. Scott
is the one who definitely needs to
he's
doing it all.
God's an angel.
>> On
the call, but he's having a hard time with the audio. So I don't think he can
>> chime in right now. So All right. He'll chime in the next one. But let's keep going. We'll put that one on the list, Eric, of things we gotta circle back to.
Mean, it really haven't changed very much, if anything.
>> No. There's not a lot that really needed changing.
Know, we're up a little bit in fire extinguisher testing.
You know, part of that is going up because we've got more we need to replace next year.
That covers both testing and annual replacement.
Diesel is up significantly,
but that's just a straight,
we're forecasting roughly the same total diesel usage by public works,
but we are paying more for it.
Gasoline,
we're
forecasting,
you know, somewhat more use than we had
accounted
for last
year.
That's really the difference in that.
You know, again, who really knows what you know gas costs are going to be.
You know, so
those are the two areas there
again that's a really variable.
As far as
snow removal goes,
you know we had dropped the budget number down for overtime snow removal
in half a couple years ago.
Down to $15,000
We certainly made that last year, you know, because it was a Maya, you know,
we were about right last year. Adrian. Gonna be under this.
Mute your phone for a bit.
>> No. It's not Adrian. I think it might be Scott calling, and now he's echoing through his computer.
>> There we go. I was gonna say I I was muted.
>> Okay. I just muted him. Sorry, Scott, if you were trying to talk.
I muted your phone though, so,
but not your other computer.
So hopefully you can still chime in.
So
that was
Jay's,
Jay Phil
was a more
realistic
number for that, for an average year.
That's what he put in his budget.
Salts,
you know, we don't have a salt contract lined up yet for next year.
You know, as most of you know, when they took the pier
for the wind energy
plant in New London,
they took away the pier where all the salt came in and it was stored
pretty much in the state.
So now we've narrowed it down from basically four suppliers that there were before
to two suppliers,
but two suppliers that both end up using the same depot.
So we're not getting,
you know, the salt costs have gone up pretty considerably.
But,
you know, depending based on our usage,
it looks like we can probably get away with, you know, around 66,000
in average.
And part of that is because
we've gone from using all treated salt
to now we use,
you know, untreated salt in the warmer parts of the winter and just reserve the treated salt for the coldest portions of the winter.
So that reflects a little bit of those savings also.
Transfer station wages,
you know, our fees in this schedule are set by contract.
Our usage has really held steady for about a year and a half or two years since we got out of the worst of the COVID portion.
So we're basically flat lining
the budget other than
the increased
fees we're seeing
that are passed on by sell.
But
remember in about a year we're going to be up for contract
renewal
and it looks like those numbers for tipping fees and bulky waste
and hauling fees are going to go up a lot.
A
lot being,
you know,
up to 25%.
Because right now we're under $100
a ton
for all those, you know, those
fees.
And it's looking like we're going to end up somewhere.
Most of the contracts are signing now are 125
a ton or greater.
So it's not going to affect us this year, but it will affect us down the road.
And that's going to be a big,
big fee.
>> So the recycling,
I haven't put in all the contracts.
The first number for hazardous waste
that we know pretty well because that budget was approved at the Midnear Rock meeting.
I still have to go through the contracts.
We have the new contracts for any freeze oil fire
and go through and put those in. I have not done that yet. But my estimates
are close.
So it's not gonna be much different than the numbers that are there.
Ground care, honestly, I don't have firm numbers for
most
of that yet.
I did put a note into Craig for an estimate for what next year would
be for the mowing.
I have the budget for beautification,
and I need to add in the money for
Also, the maintenance
of.
What do you call the.
The monument area.
So.
>> Again,
I
built in some increase in that. I'm hoping it's not more than
what it is.
Street lighting,
that's just straight off the Eversource bill. So that's assuming that Eversource charges us what they've been charging us.
Unlike the rest of our bills
for electricity,
where the supply
comes through constellation
for the street lighting that comes straight through Eversource. So we can't use a third party supplier
for that.
So which is why you see a pretty big increase year over year in that, That reflects Eversource's
rate increase
in supply.
Custodian,
you know, that's
wage
based on
what we end up with
for employees.
The resident state trooper contract, if you remember last year,
we
guessed way over
based on what
information
we got from the state on how to estimate it.
We have the same trooper.
There's nothing else that's really changed.
So I took what we are actual expenses for him last year.
And,
you know, I increased
that a little bit and used that for a number, hoping that that's more realistic,
because unfortunately they don't release
what they charge you for the indirects
until the year is over anyway.
You know, I think 140 should probably cover it, but,
you know,
that's an expense. I have very little way to to accurately
forecast.
>> You might wanna check-in
Eric, you might wanna check and see what step he's at because there was a fairly big increase in, the first five steps. I think it was almost 25%.
Really?
Okay.
>> Yep.
Yeah. I was they they had a retention issue, so they the new contract that was just agreed to
was was substantial. It's 25% on the low steps, and it kind of brought everybody's up, but
it was really substantial on the lower end. So we wanna check and see. He may be able to tell you, give you some guidance.
That's a thought.
>> So I asked him, which is what we do every year, is we ask the resident state trooper to run it up the chain and give us the gloss I've
asked him that, I just haven't gotten it yet. So yeah, maybe
totally off on that, you know, and that's way back up again. That's one of those frustrating things when I look at what we forecast
versus what we get charged,
there's really
very little correlation year to year.
We've guessed under by 25,000.
And
last year we guessed over by, you know, we budgeted 170
and got charged 128.
So,
>> you know. Yeah. That's my concern is I think he's on some of the lower end of the steps. It may be more, you know, at least his base, just take his base salary and add 25%.
So Yeah. Okay.
>> Okay. Scott wanted to share that
he called Christine
Randazzo for a number for the Veterans Park, the turf maintenance,
and he's just waiting to hear back from her about that.
>> Okay.
I did leave her a message the other day. Have not spoken to Christine,
though.
I think she's done a really good job with that. The
crabgrass
elimination
there
and the fertilization
program and weed eradication
seems to work pretty well. I mean, it's looking pretty good overall.
So I would like to continue along that same thing
and continue to use her for that.
Fire department budget. Their overall budget was up around
3%.
I do have, they did give me a breakdown budget.
I can send that to the board
if you want to review their budget.
>> We can review it, but we don't have any say over at the report to the Board of Finance.
>> Well,
that's why I haven't sent it to you so far.
But if you want to see it, I can certainly send it to you.
I had a conversation
with
NECOG about where they were going.
They have not
finalized a budget yet.
This reflects
number,
part of the increase of this reflects
a change in the
number of residents
that we have
that has gone up slightly based, I forget what formula they're using, what state
database they use for determining population of each of their members' towns.
But that
has increased.
It increased here, and that also affected the cost that we pay for because
both of those, the
population
census numbers for Andover are up.
But they do not have a final budget yet. So again, this is a preliminary number.
Fire marshal, the only thing he really asked that was significant in that
was
an increase in the training budget.
You know, and he's he basically
subscription number can come down pretty considerably
because,
you know, the descriptions,
they split the cost between the town of Andover in the town of Bolton,
or correction, Columbia anyway.
So that's that budget.
Senior citizen,
the first one is
the
contract
for Roberta.
The rest of the numbers come directly from the senior program.
So they're basically forecasting
similar.
We are forecasting
an increase in salary
You
know, for the usage to go up for the driver somewhat.
And that obviously would be somewhat dependent on
you know
their drivers would be affected by whatever we
you put in also.
I
also put in under $3.39
a,
you know, a
guess for a vehicle purchase cost.
If we're going to do it under that budget. I know you had, as a board, going back and forth whether you're going to try to fund it in this year's budget
or fund it as a budget item.
The number for Eastern Highlands Health District,
that number's
pretty solid that came out of the budget.
You know, we're,
you know,
that number for us is actually a slight decrease.
Amplify is a pretty small number.
They ask for roughly the same every year.
It's not a big
number.
Access is the access agency.
We haven't gotten official
request yet, but they typically ask for about $400
a year for the town.
They function
as our social services agency.
They're mostly state funded.
Services,
the note there is wrong. We finally had the meeting last week.
I believe I sent to both you and the Board of Finance
their
budget
to review.
They're proposing
going up around
$5,000
a little less than $5,000
in
costs
to Andover
for that program.
Have any of you reviewed that information,
the budget
stuff?
>> Yeah. You sent it over, like, over a week ago. Yep.
Does anybody have any issues or questions with that?
Because I do. The
>> the the
budget adoption, there's two votes. There's one cast on behalf of the Board of Selectmen of the Beachtown
and one cast on behalf of the Board of Finance.
You appointed me to be that rep a few years back,
but I don't cast that
vote for the budget
until you all have had a chance to review it and weigh in on it.
If you
are satisfied
with it,
I will cast the vote
that at the next meeting
on behalf of the board.
But again, that's up to you. When's the next meeting?
It has not been set yet.
I'm suspecting
the Board of Finance wants to weigh in
because they didn't have very long to review it before their last meeting.
So I think you got probably three more weeks
before you'd absolutely have to make a decision.
>> I
honestly, Jeff, if you look at the numbers, they they're really they're very conservative over there. We shouldn't have any complaints.
K.
>> I mean, the the thing that that I'm always encouraged by them
is that,
you know our.
Our
percentage
of the total bill went up a little bit because they have a levy formula, just like Ram
but it's composed of two things. It's composed of one
part
is the town populations.
And then the second part is the school age population. It's kind of a blended average.
So their budget overall went up about, I wanna say 3.5%,
but our hit was a little greater because our relative percentage of that levy
went up just a little bit.
You know, the other thing I would point out with their budget is their budget,
the towns only pay about a third of their budget and about two thirds either come from the state or as fundraising
or grant funds.
So, don't think we could replace them as our youth services agency
and do it cheaper
than what they do. So, that's my personal take on it, but I will cast a vote however
you all would like me to do.
And I don't know whether you want to make a decision on that sooner or later,
but that's certainly up to you.
As far as the
salary,
I would suggest
that you add back the first selectman salary
to this.
You know we've taken it out the last couple of years, because Mr McGuire hasn't wanted a salary,
But since we don't know who's going to be the incoming
first selectman,
I think it's appropriate to have
a, you know, some salary line item in there.
But again,
that's your that's your call. That's just my suggestion.
And I can either remove it or leave it in there at your pleasure.
Any dapers?
>> Put it back in there, but let's lower the salary. Yeah,
I think I think that's probably best bet.
>> Okay.
So
it was
4,000.
What would you like? Was it really?
No wonder he ran for this.
I need the money.
>> I know. You gotta get taxes to pay on that house. I
do. What what's the what's the what's the salary for the for the other select board members?
1,200.
>> So why don't we make that one 2,000
or 2,500?
Oh, okay. Let's make it 1,200.
>> I I don't have a problem with that, but, you know,
I don't care with the other. But I I think it I don't believe that it's because if I win
I win next time, I'm taking the 1,200.
>> Okay. Well, then it definitely needs to get reduced. So
no.
1,200.
>> Just make it even. Yeah. Yeah. Make it with every I mean I mean, Jeff does a lot of work. I'm not I'm not discarding that, but I think as a whole,
the most effective boards in this town have been boards that where everybody chips in, and I feel like our board kinda does that. I mean, everybody takes something,
whether it's Scott or Jeff or Paul or myself. So
you know?
Just make it equal.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And you you can that's certainly one option is to set them all to the same.
You know? I'm I'm I don't have any dog in the hunt. You know? You you tell me what you wanna do.
If we They don't have to
>> does anyone disagree with that? Anybody else wanna vote with Adrian and I to make it equal?
Yeah. We I'll vote.
>> Okay. That's three people.
4,800
or
whatever that difference is.
Okay.
6,000. I can't even do math. I'm sorry. Yeah. I will adjust that to 6,000.
>> K. I'm gonna do it in the other form and reference it back, but that's okay.
Board of finance,
you know the clerk wages,
I'm not really planning on increasing the wages for the board clerks this year. I think they're
reasonably well paid.
And I asked all the boards for roughly how many meetings they thought they were going to hold and the average length of meetings.
And that really hasn't changed from this year to last year, so no difference there.
Conservation
Commission,
they wanted us to add extra money in conferences,
and listed off a whole bunch of conferences they would like to take that would be next year. So that's in their
budget.
How much is that?
$525
for the year.
How many conferences are they trying to go to?
>> I don't know off the top of my head.
I can probably look back up at the supporting documentation
that they supplied and try to figure that out if you'd like.
>> I mean, if we're going to two conferences, I sort of get it. But if we're going to more than that, then, you know, maybe.
>> Well, remember, you got five or six people
five people on the vision.
So Uh-huh. You can run a run a pretty
quickly.
>> I know. I was just asking because, you know, I don't know how much this conference cost
in general. So
>> Yep.
Not a question I can answer off the top of my head.
Board of assessment appeals,
you know, that's one, I honestly don't think you should be, there should be a Board of assessment appeals salary.
You know, I honestly, I think there's a lot of other boards
that have a hell of a lot more work to do than the Board of Assessment appeals
and an annual basis, and none of them are compensated.
So I think in order of fairness,
I would set that to, I would zero that out. But because that's an elected official,
officials, that's a Board of Finance decision anyway.
>> I was gonna say, I was gonna say, I don't know that you can zero that out because it's an elected official
and it it had a salary attached to it. And maybe if you might wanna check with Carol. I thought there's a state statue on that because we I thought we'd looked at it once before.
Just food for thought.
>> Yeah,
I mean, I checked with Carol in a couple of weeks.
But I don't know of anything that prevents us. It's an elected position.
>> So is she on vacation? Is that what you're saying? Yeah. She's in Hawaii. Okay.
>> Zoning board of appeals is even
zoning agent
was,
know, pretty much
everything
was moved and put into the building department.
Cheryl still has to move the social net
into the building department.
We just decided it was better to have the zoning agent,
everything listed under the building and land use department as opposed to a standalone.
It just makes it easier to see, I think.
EDC
asked for
you to double their budget.
I think they also sent you a separate request
asking that you fund their
welcome to Andover signs also.
I don't think I've seen that yet,
or if I have,
it's buried.
But that is not
in the budget? They did send
it over.
>> Okay. So if you choose to roll that into the budget, we can add it right here under economic development.
The dues to the Tollen Chamber of Commerce are like $430
a year, which gives them about $70
of other things to do. So, they had asked that that be increased
to $1,000
a year.
You know.
In terms of the planning and zoning commission,
if
you are going to, remember we put the planner
under the
budget for
the building land use.
So
if you are going to do that you can safely reduce the legal professional line item for the Planning and Zoning Commission.
You could probably take it back down to 6,000
because
that then,
you know,
you're essentially
just covering
the cost of
the legal advice,
you know, which is basically Mark Brantz's services
and maybe occasionally
discussions with the town engineer.
So, that would be my suggestion,
but
that's predicated
on us hiring a town plan.
So,
I don't know whether you want to address that now
or later.
And Jim felt the the costs for mapping needed to go up considerably,
which
is still only a couple 100 extra dollars a year.
Inland Wetlands Commission,
not really much
change there at all. They're basically asking for the same thing they asked for last year.
Their biggest line item is for the board clerk.
The only thing I would note is that they only have two fifty dollars in their training budget.
Is something before the legislature
right now, which looks like
it may be considered favorably,
would do the same thing with the wetlands commissions
that has been done with the zoning commissions,
which is require a mandatory
number of training hours for everybody
in the commission.
So there's a possibility something will get changed legislatively
that will affect that.
But, you know,
it's hard to account for something that may or may not become law.
And the story and stays the same.
We don't really have any capital expenditures,
so the town,
the lease that was the old loader so that is no longer.
You know, no longer on there because we're counting for
the lease for the plow truck
just straight out of the public works equipment fund.
The
reval number seems like it's worked pretty well
the PO CD number
what we're talking about is
we're talking with the contractor that
the zoning
commission
prefers to hire to do the POCD,
whether they would take on and agree to be both a contract planner
and
do the POCB
as part of the planning services.
So, don't know how that's going to go. We're going to have that meeting tomorrow with the contractor,
myself and Jed.
So, hopefully, we'll, you know, all know more by the next meeting
how that's going to relate.
If we don't
do that, and we keep in what we're doing for the
POCD,
you know, we're going to have to get that contractor to lower their prices because we don't have enough money budgeted for that.
We might need to increase for this year the amount put into the POCD
capital fund.
By another $5,000
but I don't want to put it in
until we know more so we're just not there.
But we might be by the next meeting.
And the last thing I did was I put in you've seen all these before for the transfers,
other than I increased the building maintenance fund
specifically to put aside $30,000
for the renovations in the Andover Museum.
And that is basically the whole budget in a nutshell.
That's your thirty second tour of the budget.
>> Hey, Scott, good to see you.
He can't talk, but he can see we can see him.
Alright.
Well, so the items that you highlighted in yellow are things that we should circle back to at our next meeting and give you an answer on.
Okay.
Does anyone have any issues with anything Eric reviewed so far?
No. Can you hear me?
Yes. Yep. We can hear you now.
>> I see that you put in, renovations to the Andover Museum, but you can't put in
money for a temporary
worker down at the ball field.
Well, you gotta put the $30,000
>> into the I know. I know. I'm I know. I know. We didn't Scott,
>> we did not say we weren't going to sit there and fund the temporary worker. We were waiting for you.
>> I I heard what you said, Jeff, and I and you're right on target with that. I I believe all you need is somebody that
wants to be responsible
to check the irrigation in both facilities
in the morning to make sure that everything is working and to
disconnect it and connect it in the
just disconnect it in the fall and to connect it in the spring.
And and I can train someone with the in the DPW
staff
to do those things.
But we need to talk about it as a group.
>> K. Let's
do that at our next meeting. So, Eric, at our next meeting, are we well, was there anyone else that wanted to add anything to any of the issues
that have been addressed today?
>> All I'm I'm just suggesting
or
thinking
we need to in order to move this forward, we need to kinda set some,
I don't know, priorities or something, what we wanna vote on next meeting,
because we're just gonna keep looking at the same info again and again, unless somebody disagrees.
So should we set some
tasks or things that we wanna do for the next meeting? I know we we're still waiting on
public works info and some other things to fill in the blanks, but what's our goal at the next meeting?
>> Well, there was nothing that Eric reviewed today that I wouldn't vote on and say yes. He has three items I believe were highlighted in yellow that need to be addressed
for the next meetings, maybe four, if I counted them correctly.
But that's what I'm asking. Does anyone have a problem with the way that Eric has laid out
these segments? And I know we gotta go over the
public works
with Jay when he's available. And that's the significant.
I mean, there wasn't anything that really increased that significantly.
>> No, I mean, the only real decisions
that I see is you still got to make a decision on what you want to do with employees.
I can resend you those two spreadsheets
if you would like.
If you know what I'm talking about. You may as well send them to us. Okay. I'm happy to resend those.
Other than that, the one of the spreadsheets basically lists,
you know, the implications are for a 2%, 3%,
and a 4% increase,
you know, or you can
come back to me and tell me you want to look at a different number and
I'll put that back in front of
You know the
largest
increase
was what Carol asked for, but she is an elected official so ultimately that's a board of finance decision,
although you as a board can certainly weigh in on that.
So
>> Paul,
from your
request,
I would think that
Eric also send this
spreadsheet
along with the other ones.
>> Yeah, with the highlighted info. That'd be, I think, sorry to hear a little bit of hand holding. I know this is hand holding, but I think this is gonna be helpful.
>> No, I mean, job is to get you the information you want to make decisions.
You just gotta tell me what that is you want and I gotta supply it. So not a problem. And then at the next meeting, if anybody has any
>> significant personal priorities, we should discuss them and sit there and see if we can add them. Or if there's issues that people want to reduce something, we should reduce something.
I mean, there's nothing that Eric went over today that
I wouldn't vote on and say fine.
I mean, what's your total increase?
Well, when you send us the spreadsheet, we'll figure out your total increase.
Yeah.
Okay.
>> And then Eric, for next week's meeting.
So we're meeting a week from today. Does that give you and Jay time to go over what you need for that part of the budget?
>> I hope so. I mean, I'm on a commission tomorrow
because I have that tomorrow's my grant deadline. But after that,
like Thursday,
Friday, I'm okay. So, as long as I'm not thinking this is gonna be a crazy bad storm.
So I don't see any reason why the two of us can't sit down and,
you know, and spend a couple days working on that prior to the next meeting.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And then what you might've said it, but I've been kind of talking with Scott here and there. So
did you mention that you had a date that you confirmed for that?
I keep forgetting his name that was gonna come talk to us to give us a little insight on the town planner. Yeah, I did confirm a date. Unfortunately it's not what I wanted,
>> but,
you know, we can get him on the thirteenth,
which was the date you were going to adopt
the budget and send it to the board of finance.
I'm sorry. I couldn't get him before then, but he's just got a lot of commitments.
So.
>> We could just leave that for the last line item, I guess. Yeah.
>> I think
we can start obviously thinking and talking about things, but
leave that for that
>> last item like Jeff was saying. And then your other three things, don't see
any reason why we can't discuss those and approve those at the next meeting.
Yep.
>> Yep, okay.
So other than sending you the spreadsheet,
the employee salary
or employee compensation
spreadsheets,
and sending you a new copy of this draft budget sheet,
What is it? What are my deliverables?
And, you know, hopefully putting together a better
number
for what we would need to put into the road improvement fund
with Jay,
what are my deliverables for the next meeting?
>> I mean, that was it because you don't have anything.
Well, the vehicle,
I mean, even though we're putting $35,000
in it, the vehicles. So I know Jeff Murray has had some
has done some research on different items. And to be really honest, I was listening to your conversation.
The I like the van idea, Jeff.
>> Yeah. That might be that we could do it. The problem is that we're not gonna get that on the timeline we're looking at.
The other thing is we could just look at it for a free future purchase. That's what I kinda like, the hybrid technology instead of just using a pure gas minivan
down the road. Why
>> couldn't we get it on the timeline? What is the issue with that? Well, I just think it's gonna have to
>> be adapted.
We could probably reach out to these manufacturers and see what their build time is, but I'm sure it's gonna be way beyond
the delivery time that we're gonna want for this vehicle.
And
the real question is, do we need
>> Yeah, that's the problem. It's a nice to have, but it's
a nice want, but it might not be a need.
>> Right, because I mean, the reality is
it is very rare.
Right now we have three vehicles
that can all transport somebody who's handicapped.
And the majority of time we're not transporting people who are handicapped.
So, mean, that's not,
you know, it's great to have those, but you don't need another one.
You know.
>> And then when the time comes around, if we want to pursue
an electric vehicle in the future, there's
probably a dozen models on the horizon that are going to be out in the next two or three years that it would be more suited for what we'd use it for. So,
you know, I think we just need to kind of get over the hurdle with this is like, we went with the hybrid, it would be kind of a, it would be an integral step to where we would need to go eventually.
>> For the record, Jeff, I still don't agree with you on that. I still think a Bolt would be a perfect vehicle. Well, all right. So Eric, just to address that situation,
>> I actually talked to two owners that own Bolts today.
And I talked to another owner that owns a Kia
Niro
Hybrid.
And we came to the conclusion that the Bolt would be extremely too small. Bob Hamburger was completely right about that. The leg room,
it'd be hard for a senior to get in and out of it. It's just not sized appropriately.
I'm not disagreeing with you on electric, but it's just, there's nothing right now sized
in
the price point that we're looking at right now.
And that's the problem. And the thing is,
I did a lot of research and
it seems like the Toyota just came to the top, the RAV four just came to the top every time. So
just on size, use,
features,
and reliability and and
residual value. So, I mean, it's just I I took all that stuff into consideration. That's what I came up with.
>> Yeah, and right. I mean, I don't ultimately
the five of you are the deciders. I mean, I don't agree with you, but I certainly respect your right to make that decision. Whatever you decide
>> I live with. I mean, talked to one person has relative,
know, his mother is elderly
and she has an issue getting in and out of the vehicle. And so he said, yeah, if you're going to have people
that are limited mobility getting in and out of the front seat, it's going to be an issue. And he admitted he said, it's not going to be the best vehicle for senior transportation.
Bolt or Bolt EUV?
Both.
Okay.
>> So that's
from owners, people that own them personally.
The drain issue for parked is not such a big issue. The only issue is these owners, it gets cold, especially, you know, below 20 degrees,
they've noticed that their battery efficiency goes down 40%,
especially when it's not in a heated garage.
And so where are we going to be storing this?
In a non heated garage.
So
the battery technology,
did a lot of reading on it. In the future, they're going to start doing more
heating of the batteries while they charge to keep the efficiency up when they're being used.
Because once the battery is up and running,
some of the motor cooling goes back into the battery in the cell and keeps the battery warm, so the efficiency goes a lot higher. So the technology is still kind of young with that. So the next two or three years, we'll probably see a big ramp up in technology as far as efficiency in the batteries.
>> Okay. So
let's
Paula, what we'll do before the next meeting is I'll take
I'll take Eric's information, and we'll put a little list together of things that we have to vote on.
And we can vote on them at our next meeting and have an agenda for voting. I mean,
there's 90% of this budget that I would just honestly pass today,
move forward today,
unless
Well other members of the selectmen have issues.
>> Do we wanna I'm gonna I just wanna throw one thing out there. I mean, it's I was looking at the calendar today on the town website and.
I mean, I see disc golf listed. I don't see I don't see pickleball listed. I don't see.
I don't see the volleyball listed. I don't see a lot of other things listed on our website. Is it time
that we probably consider putting some money aside for a
part time recreation coordinator?
I would love to support that.
So would I, Jeff Murray.
>> If they I thought you were the part I thought I thought Scott Persson was the part time recreation commissioner.
>> I don't know if you saw the pictures, Paula and Jeff and Scott are
>> Well, I
have an issue with this whole thing because
Paula makes a big deal that people don't show up, but then she discourages people from going by saying they don't have enough rackets. So
>> just saying. Okay. It's I'm I'm just saying there's a lot of opportunities out there, and maybe we somebody on a part time basis.
It could be somebody that's that's presently employed with the town that wants to take it out. Paul goes to every event. Why doesn't apologists do it?
Yeah.
>> Because I've, you know, why not? Don't know if you've seen Biffle at our last meetings
or offices at Biffle, pickleball,
>> you know. Well, I just think this is gonna roll in with the end of the community, with new building of the community center. We're probably gonna, you know, it's gonna be a a transition period to get that
into the community center as well. If that's going be part of the senior services,
don't know. We're going to have to have somebody,
we're going to have people that are going to want to do events and one of the yoga and all kinds of things in the room.
We're going need somebody that's going to work to schedule that stuff and make sure that it's going to be
Tended. The room's left in a good condition, etcetera, etcetera.
So what are you suggesting then, Jeff?
>> I don't know. I would just throw it out there, maybe just somebody like one day a week to make sure that the website is up to date,
process some of the applications for
the classes.
I
can see all kinds of things happening in the community center, like cooking classes,
guitar lessons,
yoga,
you name it.
And we're going to have to have somebody to, we're going need somebody to coordinate all that stuff and register people and sign people up and make sure that the rooms are available at those
times they want to have those events or classes.
Right.
>> Well, look at the,
I mean, the one thing that stuck out to me and we didn't really go after it, we didn't talk about it because Eric had it as Carol reviewed,
but the rec commission, which Carol is involved in, has 6,000
for
go up, Eric, on your spreadsheet.
Sure. So Or I would there,
>> Jeff Murray, I would support 15,000 to $20,000
for that position because I do think it's important. I think we as a town,
we One
second, Adrian. Once we gave up our
athletics
in town, I do think
it stopped
bringing parents and new parents, new residents in town together to meet each other and to
become community oriented. I really do think all those events like you're doing, I think pickleball is a great idea. I think it's a great Friday night event. I think volleyball is a good thing to do.
Basketball for
the kids is a great thing to do.
Think it would be beneficial to the community to sit there and have a rec coordinator or an event coordinator that would assist the seniors,
the kids, the sports.
I think, I think it would be very positive.
>> Right. And, and I mean, I didn't overwrite
what because that is what the rec mission voted on for their budget.
But I mean their budget on programs is tight enough that I mean I bought all the pickleball nets,
you know, and just donated to the program because they didn't have any money.
You know? So it's it's not a
>> you know, it is a tight budget. I I don't disagree with I don't think I don't think it's enough money, but, again, it goes to what Jeff Murray was saying. What are the programs?
>> Because the only thing I knew about pickleball is that there was white tape down on the AES Gym floor.
And I asked somebody, what's this tape for? And they said, oh, pickleball. And I said, you know what? I didn't even know pickleball was going on.
I'm like, you know,
we're pretty tied into
what's going on at Selectmen, but the average person, citizen in town is never going to find out about this stuff unless we somehow,
either through the River East or through a coordinator. And I mean, AES is great. They send things home,
but there's a lot of kids that don't go to AES. They go to private school and other schools that don't get to
I mean, parents, I've heard from multiple parents, they don't know what's going on in town, what's available.
And we need to do a I better job of getting that out
>> agree with everything that everyone is saying, except
I think this needs to be a larger conversation about
what we're doing with community centers as far as staffing. Because I think you
may want to look at something with a
situation.
That person could also be the person that helps with the that ends up doing
mean, Cassie Plassey said very clearly she's not doing this forever. So we need to start thinking about what someone
that can be taking over that scheduling for rides and a lot of the things that are kind of falling on a volunteer's shoulders right now, we could tuck into a position
that basically
manages the community center and manages these events. Well,
>> start it
with
a small program and then
for next year, because we won't have a community center built until
at least halfway through the year
if built.
I mean, listen, I
will absolutely support that
>> issue because I Yeah, we either merged this position in with the senior services or we,
I just think for the time being,
really need to get a handle on the
programs that we have in town
and get them out there on the website and get it, because it should be on the calendar that there should be volleyball at the AES gym.
And offer more.
Because I'll tell you- Well,
>> so ask this,
has anybody in the rec commission or anybody that's part of
the pickleball
program
gone to my admin assistant and said, Hey, you need to put these events on the calendar?
>> Probably not because it's volunteer, but if there was somebody paid doing it, rounding up all these activities and making sure that they're on the website,
and then like all the registrations for sports and things that we do,
all that stuff's getting processed through that person. So they know that we're staffing teams and we're doing things,
we have enough kids to play in certain age groups and everything.
>> And the person walks across the parking lot and speaks to the teachers
and asks the teachers to make sure that the kids get their
basketball registrations and come to Saturday morning and first, second, and pre K and come to the program.
I mean, that's stuff that's not getting done.
>> Yeah, and to top that off,
there's a family in town that their son's not
going to AES and they didn't know about basketball and they were interested in playing. We kind of lost somebody.
No, we're there on Saturday. They can come. Know. Let's just Bring them. Send them. They're older, so they would be playing an elevated Okay. But
>> if you're going to put a budget together, then we need to how many hours do you want to do a week,
etcetera, etcetera? I'd say
>> eight hours a
week would be fine, I think, to start and just see where that gets us
and just budget for that.
I think that'd be acceptable. And what are paying
them an hour?
$15
>> an hour. $20 an hour. Come on. But we got this The thing is there might be a volunteer that may wanna do this, but they're just gonna get they'll be on the record and be able to get paid for what they're doing.
Because
we're we're relying way too much on volunteers to to get a lot of this stuff done, and I don't I I don't think it's fair to the volunteers.
You start adding this to someone else's position?
What's that? Add this to someone else's position possibly?
>> Possibly, it's just, it
would be a standalone position. So if
somebody was a current employee
and they were maybe part time and they wanted to take this on as an additional role, they could. What
about Eric's admin?
>> You're push her over into you're gonna no. You if you do Eric's admin, Scott, you were gonna run to the same problem we ran into in the past that we got sued over. So
Oh.
Too many hours.
>> If you take an employee, that's the part
time with benefits employees,
which would be Lauren,
You know, and the
the building department admin
eight hours a week
he couldn't do lauren because that would push her into a full time
status
and I'm not sure you necessarily wanna do that.
>> Yeah. You'd run into that problem no matter what you do. So there aren't really, don't want, how about someone from the PTA or cool? Yeah. So I'm thinking somebody it's You you yeah. You don't wanna drop this on an employee. I mean, you want somebody that wants to do this, that's excited about doing this. So
>> Well,
we we have suggested in the past what what Jeff Maguire is suggesting now.
>> Well, look. If you do $16 an hour, eight hours a week, you're at, you know,
6,600
a year. So if you put 7,000 in.
If you're gonna do it, you should also give them a little bit of a marketing budget. So maybe you put $10 in for the whole thing.
You know? Let them be able to send out flyers or something, postcards, something to try to get it out there even if it's just, like, buying an ad in the River East every now and then or something.
Yeah, I'm fine with that.
About $10?
>> Yeah, it's
just such a small segment of the budget.
And
I think it would just benefit so many more people that if they knew things that were going on, we'd get a lot more participation.
Right.
>> Yeah. Do we put this under the auspices of the rec commissioner or where do you put it?
>> I think we should probably put it under their budget. And that person, I think that person would probably answer to the rec commission.
Fair enough. It would be somebody that would report to the rec commission.
>> That's fair. Be It the person,
it would be like the
rec commission administrator
like Eric is for us. Correct. They would be. And they should be, you would hope that you would get somebody that would want to run it, really run it.
And
>> I think probably could get a few candidates in town of people that were interested.
Because I think we have people that have that vision that they wanna have some more involvement
in town with sports.
And who would they work for then?
>> I think they report to the rec commission. Like, the rec commission wanna do a program.
They would work Eric.
>> Eric. They would be reporting to Eric, though. Right? Well, they would they would report.
>> They would work for Eric. Eric has to be in charge of all employees. Exactly. Yeah. Right. From an employee standpoint, but from a directional standpoint, because
they would they would definitely take direction from the rec commission.
Right. Yeah. Right. Okay. So long sets
>> Well, we wanna be careful with that, though, because I don't know how long the rec commission meetings are, but you could burn through some of your hours just sitting in a meeting.
>> You don't have a lot of hours on this list. They're once a month. Yeah. They're once a month, Adrian. They're not that long. They're maybe an hour. Yeah. They're short. Okay.
>> Oh, you mean, like, you mean, like, this budget meeting was posted for an hour?
>> Yeah. Well, if you could get we get started till eight to 08:13
07:13.
>> Thanks, Scott. I'm sorry to throw it out there, but I just thought we not we needed to discuss it for this budget. That's all. So your goal is to basically add 10,000
>> with
the intention of getting,
hire somebody to work roughly eight hours a week at approximately $16
an hour,
for the town
to
handle everything that the rec commission does now,
but to essentially have more time available to actually manage the programs
>> and time and interact with the school. Does that accurately sum up what you're asking?
And would probably be involved with the community center once it gets up and running.
>> I I think that's an assumption to make because it doesn't you don't know what this person's skill set's gonna be. Yeah. If they're fit for
that position, then let's do it. Right. Right. But let's not make an assumption that I mean, because really what we want when we get to the community center level, I think, is we want someone that understand
or start looking for grants.
You know,
>> because there are there's a lot of programs out there. So Right. And, Eric, what did you write down in there? You put eleven five. There were six in there. Six and ten is 16.
Isn't it?
Well,
I'm not sure what you just said. What
>> are what are you adding up, Scott? What was the what was the number under the
rec commission before? $60,066,000.
So and what is there now?
>> I haven't done put anything there now.
I'm because I'm gonna have to add an actual line item
because,
you know, you can't just put employee under programs. You're gonna have to add something for an actual employee there.
So you'll have Well, about an
indirect. About
About what? How about what?
>> How about we sit there and say,
this is a priority that this board would like to put into place. We're gonna put it under the rec commission.
Let's figure out how to do it. We don't have to decide it all tonight. I mean, Jeff just brought it up. I definitely will support it. I know Scott will support it. I'll support it. So
I mean Paula will.
>> Why wouldn't she? She needs more pickleball help. Right.
Well,
you're not coming.
>> Adrian, I I didn't I didn't you want me to come? Adrian,
>> make sure that there's a racket here for you if you tell me I want you to use your Amazon
>> gifts your Amazon gifts to get pickleball rackets.
And we'll and we'll test them. We'll test them. Just make keep making excuses, Adrian. You're just scared because I'll beat you. Hey. The problem will beat you. I I have to tell you guys, though. I I really I you know, I I It's the only net she can see over, so, you know. I
go to the gym, and I sat there, and I said, who put down these white lines?
Who did that? Was it Scott? And and, Paula, were you two the ones that laid down the white line? No. Grace and Dave Gestanian.
I started to chuckle. I said, the poor kids can't figure out where the lines are on the court to begin with, and I got all of these new Too guidelines that I have to sit funny.
They
out fine.
>> They don't care. They don't care. My kids don't care about out of bounds or inbounds. It's just don't hit the wall. That's all I care about.
Like Ragged Ball.
>> That's it.
Scott brought his grandson there.
We're in. I don't know why everybody doesn't bring their kids down. Wait. Are we letting kids play pickleball?
>> I thought this was for No. This is basketball. Agent.
It is. They're old people.
>> Right. Eric, I played with Paula's
son. I'll play with him any day.
He's a very good player. It was the first time he ever played. I'd play with him any day.
Because he's very good.
He's got awesome sports capabilities
from his mom. He does. He But really
>> that's why you don't wanna play with kids because you get your butt kicked. Who wants that?
It's a move. I'd be playing against, like, George Knox.
Somebody might be able to beat up.
Don't be Jesus,
>> Jesus. Sit and
have the board selectman tournament. It's almost March. Listen, don't
>> be saying anything bad about my buddy George Knox, okay? I'm not,
>> but I think I could take him in pickleball, pretty sure. I don't know. He's, He's you know got better lateral movement than you. That's true.
>> He's getting better by the minute. Go. Do we have anybody out here? Like, let's let's all of you organized for our next meeting. I gotta go home.
My my wife will be wondering where I am.
I'm
texting her right now that you're a pickleball.
>> Yeah. Good for me.
Is
there anything specific that I mean, so let's just bring our agenda to next meeting. We'll vote on all of the items that Eric went through. If you have any items that are in the budget that you want to sit there and call out,
we'll sit there and address them at the next meeting. And then Eric, when are you getting
Jay? When do you want to do Jay? Do you want to do it the next meeting? Do you want to do it the following meeting?
>> I am hoping we're doing it at the next meeting.
>> Can we just throw an agenda up for the next meeting that's got a list of all the things you want to vote on?
Sure.
>> I think Eric's the three things other than the planner, right? We want to vote on those.
Want to vote on the
town employees, salary increases,
and then public works.
>> And then are we are we Money for rec commission.
Money for rec commission. Money for the car.
>> And, yeah, Eric, is there any way we can get a solid quote for that vehicle that that vehicle by next Monday?
Probably not, but,
you know, it's possible.
Alright. Then the answer is probably.
>> So let's sit there and see if we probably can get a quote. Can we, yeah, can we just let the dealer just get a budgetary
>> Just to make sure we're in the price range we need to If you if you call a dealer, they'll get back to you within a day.
>> They wanna sell it. Right. I I mean, that's that's something
that's an estimate. That's not a a price quote would be something through Sourcewell
or something the purchasing
policy would allow us to actually execute.
>> Right. But Sourcewell would be cheaper, right? So, than a regular deal? Yeah, if we just get a budgetary quote directly from the dealer, just have a call from a municipality
and we're looking for mid level trim
vehicle.
Why?
It's a budget.
>> It's a budget. We don't want it. Just let's sit there. We need something with adjustable pedals and stuff just in case Paula wants to volunteer to drive too.
Bring in her own pickleball team.
Paula.
Wow.
This is being recorded, number one.
>> Well, listen. Paula and I are going I'm going pickleball, and I'm I'm with Paula. I'm going Paula and I are playing. Okay.
Be prepared to be crying.
>> There you go, basic model, whatever. We
just got to get something to vote on for price.
>> To put in the budget. Paul, we'll sit there and Let's do
get a list of things that we want to vote on. Everybody contribute to the next agenda so that we vote on what everybody has
or needs to vote on.
And then we'll do the rest of the budget as a global
get her done And
>> Eric, if you run into trouble, if you need budgetary pricing, I could probably help you this week.
If
you want me to do that on your behalf, I can do that as well. All right, so since we scared away every member of the public,
>> and they didn't want to participate in our
banter,
then
we
can make a motion to adjourn.
Motion to adjourn. Motion to adjourn.
>> All right. Adrian seconded
that. All those in favor?
Aye. Aye.
We'll see you. Paula, you you